A Guide to the Correspondence of Charles Tenney with Adelaide Case, 1861-1863
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
- Adelaide Case Letters 1861-1864, 59 letters
  - Adelaide Case Letters, 1861, 14 letters
    - Mecca, October 3, 1861
      Addie says a presentiment of evil has been hanging over her head and fears Charlie is ill or wounded. She wants to send Charlie a book her friend Dora has been assembling as a gift.
    - Mecca, October 12, 1861
      Addie says she has received Charlie's letter from Charleston. She finds Mecca dull and lonely and urges Charlie to accompany Hal if he comes home.
    - Mecca, October 16, 1861
      Addie says heavy snowfall brings hope of sleigh rides and parties. She thinks General Freemont (John Charles) is treated unfairly and is more capable than General Hunter (David). Addie mentions that she takes more pleasure in writing to Charlie than any of her other correspondents except Hal. She is disdainful of Charlie's request that she burn his letters, and instead says she will keep them in a box in her trunk.
    - Mecca, October, 27, 1861
      Addie remarks on the eagerness with which she awaits Charlie's letters and says she does not object to Charles's flattery of her. She attended a recent Union ball in which Charles's captain told her that he (Charles) "is one of the best boys in the regiment."
    - Mecca, December 7, 1861
      On flag stationary which reads "Long May It Wave," Addie writes that she has received only one letter from Charlie since September. She tells of a gentleman caller named James Beebe whom she detests, and she relates amusing story about his call. Addie also laments the evils of slavery.
    - Mecca, December 19, 1861
      Addie poignantly describes her prayers for Charlie, but only as a "loving sister would pray for a brother." She says she has resisted feelings other than sisterly.
    - East Mecca at Aunt Sperry's, December 19, 1861
      Addie says she thinks she will go to Oberlin in February to attend school.
    - Mecca, December 26, 1861
      Addie thanks Charles for sending her his sketch of camp. She writes that she has sent him a very painful letter concerning their relationship.
  - Adelaide Case Letters, January- June 1862, 32 letters
    Thirty-two letters from Addie to Charlie from January- June 1862 describe the deepening relationship between the two, with Addie accepting Charles' proposal of marriage and admitting deep protestations of love for him. During this period, the two finally exchange portraits of each other. Addie also starts school teaching in East Claridon, Ohio, and writes often of her experiences, including reading of the Bible to her pupils, problems of discipline and the interesting times she has "boarding out" with various families. Addie comments often on the war, particularly the Battle of Winchester, in which Charlie received a slight wound, and describes some of the women's activities to help on the home front.
    - Mecca, January 1, 1862
      Addie thanks Charlie for his Christmas gift to her of his portrait, and she reflects on the war as church bells ring in the New Year.
    - Mecca, January 10, 1862
      Addie writes that she is not attending any parties as there are none, she beseeches Charlie to take care of her ill brother, and she says Mecca, which had been called "Oildom" because of its oil supplies "is now Mecca again."
    - Mecca, January 12, 1862
      Addie wonders if it is wrong to write on the Sabbath. She gives a lengthy commentary on the evils of war and peril to the country and intends to start for Oberlin in a month.
    - Mecca, January 26, 1862
      Addie writes a long letter in which she reveals her deepening feelings for Charlie, thanks him for the original poem he has sent her, and laments the fact that General McClellan is forbidding furloughs.
    - Mecca, February, 2, 1862
      Addie addresses her letter to "darling Charlie" and fervently expresses her deepening love. She thanks him for writing that he is "free from dishonor."
    - Mecca, February 3, 1862
      On flag stationary and in a romantic and poetic letter, Addie thanks Charles for the sketch he has sent her of his camp; says she is flattered at his thoughts on receiving her portrait. She also expresses sorrow that so many officers of the Ohio 7th are resigning.
    - Mecca, February [4], 1862
      Addie merrily describes activities of groups at Union Hall of the "Soldiers' Aid Society. She says "Oil City" is not dead and describes some of the wells still in operation.
    - Mecca, February 9, 1862
      In a largely illegible letter, Addie muses about how to handle their correspondence with other people, and she wonders how Charlie ever chanced his "abrupt question to a little country rustic like myself."
    - Mecca, February 9, 1862
      Addie weeps "tears of joy" at the receipt of Charlie's letter and comments on her foolishness at thinking she could disguise her love as being only sisterly.
    - Mecca, February 11, 1862
      Addie says she enjoyed Charles' "diary letter," dreads prospects of fighting on the Potomac, and answers Charlie's apparent proposal with a request to let things remain as they are until she can make herself worthy of him.
    - Mecca, February 13, 1862
      Addie sends her portrait to Charles and writes town news including story of man who killed his wife of two months.
    - Mecca, February 18, 1862
      Addie describes a dream in which she struggled to reach an ill Charlie and bemoans the fact that she has not heard from him. She tells of a school room where she is teaching with "fifty scholars" ranging from five to twenty years of age. She also tells of her religious views.
    - Mecca, February 23, 1862
      Addie muses over her evolvement from "friend" to "sister" to "sweetheart."
    - Mecca, February 25, 1862
      Addie says "yes" in answer to question as to whether she loves Charlie, and she sends him a miniature of herself as a "sacred gift" and true expression of her love.
    - Oildom, visiting Dora, March 12, 1862
      Addie is visiting her sister Dora, but she plans to go home as school closed two weeks ago. She is sad has not heard from Charlie for a long time.
    - Maple Grove, March 23, 1862
      Addie reflects on her love for Charlie and tragedy of soldiers' deaths.
    - Mecca, March 23, 1862
      Addie says she came home Friday, but has not received any mail from Charlie. She says, "my precious one, my heart, my idol, my all."
    - Mecca, April 1, 1862
      Addie receives Charlie's letter of 25th and learns of his wounds in battle.
    - Mecca, April 8, 1862
      Addie is dubious about Charlie's statement that the 7th is "all safe" after the battle of Winchester. She says she passed through a wretched week after battle.
    - Mecca, April 13, 1862
      Addie says the battle of Pittsburg Landing has been much on her mind. She very much wants a full length photo of Charlie.
    - Mecca, April 16, 1862
      Addie sends Charlie some pressed flowers. She comments on the beautiful weather and how life is to be enjoyed, discusses Mecca news, and she reports she is to start teaching in one week in Claridon, Ohio. She says she hates the "letter blockade."
    - Maple Grove, April 20, 1862
      Addie tells Charlie she would not have considered teaching without his approval.
    - East Claridon, May 5, 1862
      Addie says the banks of little Cuyahoga are the "loveliest place I have ever been in," she discusses her first day of school and her pupils, and she says that being a school marm is a great place to study human nature. She mentions that some lady pupils are as old as she.
    - East Claridon, May 6, 1862
      Addie says she received Charlie's letter from the 28th. She says she opens school with a chapter from the Bible and has "scholars" memorize selections of their choice. She asks Charlie what she should do about two young girls who won't read the Bible because the whole family are "infidels." She describes Claridon and its people and is thankful that the "letter blockade" is over.
    - Claridon, May [16], 1862
      Addie comments on Charlie's report of a little Southern girl "hating Yankees" and says Yankee girls would sacrifice lives to protect the flag. She describes the first of her experiences of "boarding out."
    - East Claridon, May 18, 1862
      Addie discusses the influence music has on her and (con't 5-19) describes second night of "boarding out."
    - Schoolroom, East Claridon, May 26, 1862
      Addie pines for letter from Charlie and tortures herself with thought of his death(con't 5-27), and in an attempt to be more cheerful, describes her school. She finally receives two letters from Charlie.
    - Schoolroom, East Claridon, May 27, 1862
      Addie has reread Charlie's letters of the 9th and 11th and thinks Charles has a "noble spirit." She describes her experience in punishing a 14-year-old "scholar" who cursed. She said she made him read the Bible to her and thereby converted him to better behavior.
    - East Claridon, June 4, 1862
      Addie muses about her school, 30 scholars from 4 to 17 years old, who study writing, arithmetic, geography, grammar, algebra and orthography, and she lists the names of texts used. She asks Charlie what he thinks of the retreat of General Banks and discusses her views of the occupation of Winchester. She also tells of her feelings of very old and very young men going to war.
    - East Claridon, June 14, 1862
      Addie has learned of the Battle of Shiloh and hopes fervently that Charlie can come home. She describes a conversation with head of family at one of her boarding places who was "half secesh" and who sees nothing to fight for.
    - East Claridon, June 18, 1862
      Addie has received Charlie's letter from the 5th, she discusses retreat from Winchester and says she has heard that Rebels have mutilated the monument to Mrs. (George) Washington.
    - East Claridon, June 24, 1862
      Addie says her brother Hal has reenlisted, she describes hardships endured by women with "suspense over their soldiers eating their hearts away. She thinks its providential that Charlie was impelled to remain at Luray while rest of regiment went on to Port Republic.
  - Adelaide Case Letters, July- December, 1862, 28 letters
    In twenty-eight letters between July and December 1862, Addie talks often of her deep love of Charlie. The war is intensifying, and she often has opinions of various battles--Culpeper, Chambersburg, Sharpsburg- -and many Generals--McClellan, Pope, McDowell. Sadly, toward the end of the year, she learns of Charlie's deteriorating health and often expresses her grave concern, writing at one time that her life would be a "wilderness" if Charlie did not return.
    - East Claridon, July 2, 1862
      Addie has heard an unconfirmed report that Richmond has fallen (con't 7-3) last night and heard of desperate fighting in Richmond. She heard that 1200 Union soldiers were "lying cold and insensible upon the field," and is tortured by the thought that Charlie might be among them.
    - Colebrook, July 6, 1862
      Addie writes on her way home from East Claridon for a 3-week vacation from school during haying. She has received Charlie's letter of the 21st and comments on Charlie's punishment he received for walking on the railroad tracks. She says people are losing confidence in General Shields and delights in Charlie's description of a storm.
    - Mecca, July 17, 1862
      Even though miles apart, Charlie's words strengthen Addie during separation. She thinks her life would be a "wilderness" if Charlie and her brother Hal were killed and remarks that Hal writes that if both are found dead on the field at Richmond, their last words would be "Onward to victory and Union!".
    - East Claridon, July 31, 1862
      Addie says her school resumes Monday, and she is glad to be useful again. She describes attending an Aid Society meeting and expresses her views on McClellan versus Pope and her fears that England will enter war on the Union side. She thinks women would be able and willing to shoulder arms.
    - Schoolroom, East Claridon, August 11, 1862
      Addie describes an incident in which she had to punish young female student with two blows with her hand. She comments on a line in Charlie's letter to her in which he writes "My life is nothing if by its sacrifice my country can be saved," and Addie adds that such a sacrifice would also sacrifice her life.
    - East Claridon, August 18, 1862
      Addie has heard of the battle at Culpeper and expresses great fear that Charlie has been injured but has faith in God to protect him.
    - East Claridon, August 31- September 1 (cont.), 1862
      Addie tells of constant rumors of sacrifice and defeats on the Rappahannock and gives her description of friends who are considered "cowards."
    - East Claridon, September 10, 1862
      Addie is grieving because she has not heard from Charlie. She reads that Washington is in danger, Rebels are in force in Maryland, Ohio is invaded, and she is very upset with complacent attitude of fellow townspeople who say "Lincoln means to let them whup us."
    - East Claridon, September 10-11, 1862
      Addie pines for Charlie as "surely man was never more worthy of my love than my noble, true-hearted Charlie." She also thinks Hal may come home soon.
    - East Claridon, September 16, 1862
      Addie has finally received Charles' letter and feels the war picture is "dark and gloomy," but she is glad of Charlie's confidence in McClellan is unshaken for "here his star is fast waning." She says the defeat of General Pope was attributed to the failure of McClellan to bring up his troops because they "were too demoralized to trust them on the field." Addie adds that her school closes "next week."
    - Clevaland, at Dora's home, September 22, 1862
      Addie longs for Charles' return and comments again on unfavorable opinion of many in Ohio of McClellan. She has long discussion of attitudes of Ohioans about the war.
    - Mr. Holcomb's residence, near Mecca, September 28, 1862
      In an answer to Charlie's letter of the 21st, Addie wonders how she ever lived without Charlie and asks if he has any regrets.
    - Unknown Location, October 4, 1862
      Addie is visiting her uncle's house as "maid of all works" while her aunt is away. She answers Charles' letter from the 25th and comments on his being in Virginia overlooking the Blue Ridge and wants him to describe it to her. She says her love of country is paramount to "everything but God and you." Addie gives glowing opinion of the "gallant Seventh Ohio." She says she is listening to Uncle reading about battle of Sharpsburg and watching him wipe away tears and remarks sadly on General Hooker's wounds. She says people in Ohio now more enthusiastic about McClellan and comments on character of Generals Pope and McDowell.
    - Mecca, October 4-12, 1862
      On pink Eagle U.S. stationary, Addie writes that she has two letters from Charlie, one from the 18th of August and another the 20th of September, and says she is more interested in hearing about Charlie's adventures than travels of Generals. She chastens him for thinking he writes too "politically" and describes reports of different battles in Missouri and Chambersburg.
    - Mecca, October 25, 1862
      Addie writes that Hal is now a Colonel but has difficulties getting men for his regiment. She wants to know how he could move his "mansion" he erected in the move of the camp. She remarks on General Pope being outflanked for failure to post pickets.
    - Mecca, November 2, 1862
      Addie learns of Charles' illness and hopes he has fully recovered; she hadn't realized he was so ill.
    - Mecca, November 9, 1862
      Addie has "blues" because hasn't heard from Charlie in two weeks and knows he is ill. She talks of his sister Laurie's upcoming wedding. She is glad Vallandingham (Clement Laird) was defeated as considers him a traitor. Even in Mecca are "Knights of the Golden Circle" dedicated to preserving slavery, which she hates.
    - Mecca, November 16, 1862
      Addie says it has been three weeks since has heard from Charlie. She says Laurie is married, and she is sorry McClellan was removed and thinks his undoing came from scheming politicians.
    - Farmington, November 23, 1862
      Addie writes she has learned of Charles' illness and is suffering for him; she is glad he is in current position rather than performing the arduous duties of camp. She likes her new school she is attending in Farmington where she is studying Algebra, Latin and Music.
    - Farmington, December 8, 1862
      Addie has for several days had "unwelcome forebodings" because has not heard from Charlie and spent yesterday reading all of his old letters, which detail all his troop movements thus far.
    - Farmington, December 10, 1862
      Addie has received his "dear" letter from the 25th and is so happy, though greatly disturbed because his health is so impaired. In response to his request, she gives him advice on an application for a discharge. She says that though it might seem unpatriotic of her, she feels they both have done their duty.
    - Farmington, December 17, 1862
      Addie has heard nothing since last letter and is agonizing between hope and despair over whether Charlie will be discharged. She describes her daily routine as a student.
    - Farmington, December 28, 1862
      Addie has received letters from the 15th,18th, and 19th and is saddened by news of his deteriorating health. She prays feverishly that God will let strangers care for him tenderly.
    - Farmington, December 31, 1862
      Addie writes that Charles' love has sustained her through the past year, though the year has been sad for the country except "thank God tomorrow slavery ceases." She comments on evils of slavery and consequences it has provoked and bemoans fate in not being with "beloved Charlie."
  - Adelaide Case Letters, January 1864, 3 letters
    Three letters in January of 1864, one to two friends of Charles, tell of Addie's growing alarm over Charlie's illness and her pleas for kind treatment of him.
    - Farmington, January 7, 1863
      Addie worries greatly because has not heard from Charles.
    - Farmington, January 15, 1863
      In a kind letter from Messers. Coon and Barnum, Addie learns that Charlie has received a furlough but has suffered a relapse and may not be able to take it. She describes a dream in which she is transported to a hospital with wounded soldiers where she finds Charlie
    - Farmington January 15, 1863
      Addie writes to Messers. Barnum and Coon and thanks them for their kindness to Charlie and asks them to "watch over Mr. Tenney as though he were as dear to you as he is to me."
  - Adelaide Case Letters, Fragmented and Undated
    At Maple Grove, probably during the winter of 1861 or 1862, Addie is visiting her Aunt and chit chats about family matters. In one marked the 17th, Addie describes life at home and her desire to read Pope's translation of Homer's "Iliad;" in a partial note she comments on Catholicism and wonders why they are not permitted to read "The Holy Word." Another partial letter contains family news and a description of her Father's love for her, and another gives an account of telling her Father about Charles' marriage proposal and "seeing him weep."